Right. So um
today's suta is sanga
46.6 kundalia kundalia
and um
it says um
okay it's all in order.
Um so it's a kundalia suta and it begins
by saying that the blessed one was
dwelling at saketa in the de park at the
anjenna grove the wanderer kundalia
approached the blessed one and exchanged
greetings with him once they concluded
the greetings and cordial talk he said
to the blessed one master
I'm the one who stays around the
monastic parks and frequents assembly
Assemblies after the meal when I have finished my
after the meal when I have finished my
breakfast in my custom to roam and
wander from park to park from garden to
garden. There I see aetics and brahinss
engage in discussion for the benefit of
rescuing their own thesis in debate and
condemning the thesis of others. But
what is the benefit the master goma
lives for?
Then the Buddha replies
that lives for the benefit and fruit of
the true knowledge and liberation.
Master Gautma, what things when
developed and cultivated fulfill the
true knowledge and liberation?
The seven factors of enlightenment when
developed and cultivated fulfill the
true knowledge and liberation.
What things when developed and
cultivated fulfill the seven factors of
enlightenment? The four establishment of establishments
The four establishment of establishments
of recollection kundalia when developed
and cultivated fulfill the seven factors
of enlightenment.
But master got bad things when developed
and cultivated fulfilled the four
establishment of recollection.
Three kinds of good conduct. Kundalia
when developed and cultivated fulfilled
the four establishment of recollection.
What things when developed and
cultivated fulfill the three kinds of
good conduct? And the Buddha says well
when developed and cultivated um it's
restraint of the sense faculties that
fulfills the three kinds of good
conduct. And then the Buddha begins to explain
And then the Buddha begins to explain
from that beginning
um how is the restraint of the sense
faculties developed and cultivated so
that it fulfills the three kinds of good
conduct. So it says here kundalia having seen an
So it says here kundalia having seen an
agreeable form with the eye au does not
coveret for it or delight in it or
generally generate lust for it.
His body is steady and his mind is
steady. Inwardly well settled and well
freed. Having seen a disagreeable form
with the eye, he's not dismayed by it,
not daunted, not dejected, without ill
will. His body is steady and his mind is
steady. Inwardly well settled and well
freed. So then it goes on for all the
senses. Having heard an agreeable sound
with the air, smelt an agreeable order
with the nose, savor agreeable taste
with tongue, felt an agreeable tactile
object with the body. Having cognized an
agreeable mental phenomenon with the
mind, Biku does not cover for it or
delight in it or generalize for it
um and remains inwardly steady body and
mind.
So it says uh when kundala after he has
seen the form with the eye a big body is
steady and his mind is steady inwardly
well settled and well freed in regard to
the both agreeable and disagreeable
forms and then sound smell taste touches
and phenomena. A big body is steady his
mind is steady inwardly well settled
then his restraint of the said sense
faculties has been developed and
cultivated in such a way that it
fulfills the three kinds of good
conduct.
So you could see how through perfecting
the sense restraint, obviously we're
going to go into details on how to do
that. U perfecting the sense restraint
fulfills the three kinds of good conduct
as in um
you don't really need to add much more
on the top of the sense restraint. If
you do it in regard to the six senses
rightly um and do things on the right
level, the the the the three kinds of
good conduct will uh align themselves to
put it that way. So you wouldn't have to
then start behaving properly so to
speak. So how are then the three kinds
of good conduct that you can now discern
having being fulfilled on account of
proper sense restraint? How could you
cultivate them so that they fulfill
things further
such as fulfill the four establishment
of recollection the satipatana
he says here condundalia having
abandoned the bodily misconduct au
develops good bodily conduct having
abandoned verbal misconduct he develops
good ver verbal conduct having abandoned
mental misconduct he develops good
mental conduct it is in this way that
the three kinds of good conduct are
developed and cultivated so they fulfill
the four establishment of recollection
Um
so um
yeah let's go to studatanas and then um
I can address the other questions. So
how are the four establishments of
recollection developed and cultivated
they fulfill seven factors of
enlightenment. So besides maintaining perspective of
So besides maintaining perspective of
the body concurrently with the body
orally translated contemplating body
within the body aren't clearly
comprehending recollected having removed
covetousness and displeasure in regard
to the world. So as you can see in order
to practice the satipana correctly
that requires the fulfillment of three
types of good conduct i.e. purification
of your virtue of your behavior by body,
speech and mind. Not just you know
keeping the precepts or something and
not making any further effort to
mentally um
approve the things or at least endure
them on the right level you know on that
mental level when like thoughts of
sensuality or um ill will arise and
similar. So what this illustrates is
like what many of those um uh short
sutas in sadipatana suta I think there
like half a dozen of them one after the
other where it says basically how to
practice um satipatana
and it says um well you practice
satipadana on top of the uh being
established in virtue being uh fully
bringing your virtue to fulfillment and
purification. In other words, there is
no practice of satipana unless you would
have already um well maybe not
necessarily fully realized sapati but
certainly established in your virtue
properly not just you know I adhere to
the precepts because the authority
um laid them upon me but more like I
train in the precepts by body by speech
and the mind that's the core of the
training very much what the suta
describes I mean it it started by saying
liberation Like complete enlightenment
is predicated upon seven enlightenment
factors which is predicated upon for
upon satipana which is predicated upon
right conduct of the body, speech and
mind which is predicated upon sense
restraint. So liberation is predicated
upon sense restraint.
It's not a separate thing. Um that's why
it's like as I said even as the suta
says it fulfills the next step. In other
words, if you just stick to sense
restraint and keep refining the same
principle on the body, speech and mind
level, you will be liberated.
You could you could forget everything
else in between that that the suta says
because there were cases in the sutas
exactly that when monks and nuns
approach the Buddha and all they heard
in terms of instruction was abandon
everything you know it's unh wholesome
by body speech and mind and cultivate
everything you know it's beneficial by
body speech and mind and that was enough
for them. So they stuck to it and it
would have saturated all the necessary
levels to put it that way. But obviously
you know there are le there are stages
to be discerned in between. But it's not
like that when the mindfulness the
satipathana stage begins you can forget
about a virtue and you can forget about
a sense restraint. Simply through
practicing sense restraint you would be
recognizing now existing stage of
satipatana in you
which all points to the fact that if you
have not been practicing sense restraint
withdrawal from sensuality uh celibacy
the precepts virtue that whole thing
there is no satipana regardless of what
modern terravada tells you because
you'll often hear like no no no anybody
anybody who has any idea of what body
within the body or feeling within the
feeling or any satipana means any idea
you get about it do that that's that's
satipadana well not according to this suta or most
well not according to this suta or most
of the other sutras um first in order to
have it applicable to you you need to
work your way towards it so unless you
are already uh uh investing lots of
effort in purifying your behavior your
intentions body speech and mind no
amount of attempts at satipatana will
translate into actual satipana. Putting
aside the whole like you know ridiculous
notion of being a form of mechanical
technique let's not even get into that
but even if say you're trying to be
mindful correctly not in terms of visuda
technique you still won't have a basis
for it because the virtue is not there.
Why is the virtue not there? Well
because you're still giving into your
senses. Why are you still giving into
your senses? Well, because you haven't
uh realized, haven't integrated
sufficiently enough the the value of
sensory train, the importance. You you
still think it's optional. You still
think it's negotiable
when it comes to the practice. And
that's basically a grave error in terms
of because you will end up spending
years of thinking you're practicing when
you're not.
As simple as that.
So
when the virtue is established,
when one is pretty much aligned with the
right view in terms of u purification
from the unbeneficial
actions by body, speech and mind and
during things on the right level then
you can be recollecting. You could be uh
you could be maintaining the perspective
of the body concurrently with the body,
mind concurrently with the mind
phenomena and so on. Because in order to
do satipanas as this suta says and there
are other sutras as well, they even more
explicitly state you need to be free
from five hindrances
not temporarily suppressed but actually
fully withdrawn from kind of the same
prerequisite like for the Janna. And
that's exactly what this what this
passage here what this uh sentence
means. Having removed covetousness and
displeasure in regard to the world. So
in regard what is the world? Well, the
world is is basically your six internal
sense bases with its six external
counterparts. So anything
anything that you can see, hear, smell,
taste, touch, think and background to
that it's the world.
And now you would have steadied your
mind in terms of covetousness and
displeasure any resistance. So you could
see what level of training has already
been accomplished so that satipatanas
are fulfilled as the suta say. So you
could it's completely upside down this
idea that anybody can do satipana
because it helps you in this way or that
way. Um which is also why I said like if
you come to the level of satipana now
you know because the Buddha did instruct
this to newly ordained monks you know
monks that that have not yet say had
fruition of the right view and so on but
means they already have
left the household life practice sense
restraint dwelling restrained by the
rules of the patio moa um eating once a
day being completely celibate all these
requirements and then the Buddha said
listen monks you should do this because
it will obviously bring your right view
to fulfillment and lead you one way only
to liberation.
Um but somehow the the commentary and
modern terravada and just general the
idea extrapolated that means anybody can
do this and and quote those paragraphs
to to support the ideas that anybody who
wants who declares themselves a Buddhist
can start this practice ignoring the
prerequisites even for those in those
very sutas that are being quoted
um that they already would have
fulfilled. So if you are already living living
So if you are already living living
fully celibate withdrawn from the world
uh eating once a day dwelling in
seclusion even as a householder then
sure try satipatana purifying your
behavior on the level of the body speech
and mind yeah then you could say well
you could try satipatana now you could
you could start looking into
recollecting and maintaining perspective
of the body within the body mind within
the mind because you are seeing chitta
you're seeing the mind you would have
already uh contained it enough through
right behavior but that's usually not
how it's taught today isn't it so anyway
then the Buddha says if you fulfill the
four factors of enlight four four
satanas you then bring the seven factors of
you then bring the seven factors of
enlightenment to fulfillment and then if
you maybe develop and cultivate that
maybe develop and cultivate that
specific aspect a bit more within
obviously the whole arrangement of the
previous factors none of them disappears
then that to fulfill knowledge and
liberation. So
So
here kundalia aiku develops the
enlightenment factor of recollection
which is based upon seclusion dispassion
sessation maturing and release
i.e leading you towards nibbana,
investigation of phenomena, energy, joy,
calm, samadi, composure.
So samadi is a result of the right
practice of the of the of the right
buildup. It's not something you just do
to get the right buildup.
So he develops the and then finally he
develops the enlightenment factors
factor of equinimity which is based upon
seclusion, dispassion, sessation.
So sessation of attachments, dispassion,
seclusion from everything unh wholesome,
maturing in release means maintaining
that sufficient amount of time.
So that it leads you to nibbana.
So it's not it's not it's not a it's not
a momentary thing or like a quick in and
out or something. So in this way that
when the seven factors of enlightenment
are developed and cultivated, they
fulfill true true knowledge and
liberation. And then wanderer kundalia
was very impressed said magnificent
the da has been made in clear in many
ways by master as as though he were
turning upright what has been turned
upside down revealing what was hidden
showing the way to the one who was lost
holding up a lamp in the dark. I go for
the refuge and so on. So um
so yeah so as I said the um in the
beginning the like the you could see the
the the pattern say the the structure of
the suta and it's pretty much the the
gradual training as it always is as it
always has to be
um so
the sequence of this training is not
really optional as I said despite what
what uh contemporary or ary kind of
Buddhism will try to tell you
um the vast majority of the sutas
well all of them if you read them
rightly but say if somebody who reads
them who's like neither here nor there
in terms of their views the vast
majority of the sutas clearly outlines
what needs to be done and repeats it
over and over and over again as I said
most of the satipatana sutas in um in
that sutikaya then there's that
majimanaya suta where um where a young
monk was um being talking to a king and
then uh he couldn't kind of instruct him
rightly to a young prince and then the
Buddha told him that similar about being
on top of the mountain and another
friend is at the bottom of the mountain
and then the friend at the bottom of the
mountain can't have the same sight and
views as the one on the top. But if he
decides to climb up and go all the way
up, he will share the same view. Um
implying that you need to start to do
this in order to understand it. You
can't just from the position of being
immersed in sensuality because that's
what it says that prince was like
intoxicated with his wives and harams
and whatnot. It's like there's no way he
could have understood what this monk was
sort of telling him about. uh and in
that sut the Buddha outlines the gradual
training and part of that includes
satipana which basically uh quite
clearly states when when when the biku
is like fully established in virtue
withdrawn impeccable sila sense
restraint body speech and mind solitude
then satipatana's free from hindrances
then satipatana can can be uh discerned
as another layer that now you can
develop on its own. So um that sense of
uh that that that term that occurs in
the sort of the fulfillment as I said
begins from the sense restraint and it
never stops the sense restraint
continues uh fueling
all the subsequent development. So it's
like the I don't know the the spring
that starts from the top of the mountain
where the water gathers starts to fill
the pools at the lower that then fills
up and then continue filling the next
pool the next pool and all the way down
to the mountain where they fill up the
lakes and and and oceans and so on.
Um so that's why yes as I said already
like you could you could say that um
everything pretty much boils down to
taming your senses which
rightly say uh confines and contains
your mind and primes it for the training
for the obedience training of that wild
animal as we often talk about. So that's
why it's like when this when the sa says
you know like oh he his chitta his mind
is steady
uh in regard to sight sounds smell taste
touches and thoughts so people think ah
I must steady the mind tell me what what
I do what do I concentrate at on with to
steady my mind to make it make it
unmovable you don't it's not your doing
that would be like how do I calm the
wild animal tell me how to pin it down,
how to hold it, how to uh join lock it
or something so it doesn't move. Well,
it's still going to be a wild animal.
Even if you make it motionless, it's
still a wild animal and it's not going
to be tamed on account of that um
fabricated as I said uh uh confinement.
So you study chitta in regard to sight,
sounds, smell, taste, touches and
thoughts by not acting out towards sight, sounds,
by not acting out towards sight, sounds,
smell, taste, touches and thoughts.
Initially that doesn't feel enough.
That's why people like you know I know
very well it's not like they you know
that that these meditation techniques
and contemporary views are kind of some
grand scheme plan to deceive people. No,
it just comes out of ignorant mind
naturally because when you start the
sense restraint and everybody would when
they start reading the sutas because
it's just more than obvious that it's
about that but it doesn't feel enough
like the sense restraint on its own it
doesn't feel like it's doing much you
start restraining but the mind is still
wild now it's even worse
duka increases even more becomes even
more acute so it's like so okay so how
do I deal with this with this inside
sure I I'll keep the restraint, I'll
keep the virtue, but how do I keep the
mind from from making me suffer? And
that's when they give in basically to
these views, to these tendencies and end
up overshooting the mark, end up
introducing technique, concentrations,
state of self hypnosis, oblivion to
basically dull the pain,
dull the pain,
but instead you need to stay with the
wild animal. So that's where the element
of faith comes in because you do have a
strong urge to okay I'm keeping the
precept I'm restrained but let me now
also calm down this animal
and that's the problem you still don't
see the animal for what it is so what
you're really trying to calm is just
rooted in completely your idea well your
view of pain is averse I'm averse to
pain and I don't want it I want to get
rid of it So any calming that you do out
of that impatient attitude, any
technique, any meditation that you do
will be coming out of the wildness of
that animal, will be coming out of the
craving, will be coming out of
sensuality, will be coming out of ill
will, will be coming out of hindrances
as the sutas very often say. So instead
of giving into that let me comment just
recognize hold on let me review if there
is any other like form of unbeneficial
behavior that I'm engaging with by body
speech and mind and let me correct that
and then let me leave that let me wait
let me wait for it to mature towards
release how the sutra would say
and then you recognize oh that is
already actually confining containing
steadying the chitta rightly
So you don't need to do anything on top
of it. That's the beauty of it. Once you
recognize this, that's the establishment
in the virtue. That's the aggregate of
virtue. That's like what I often say um
you come to the point of like really uh
internalizing recognizing that oh I
don't know what I should do or
necessarily always or I don't know what
I might do but I will know what I will
not do. So recognizing things that won't
be done gives you that sense of
confinement and and and but positive
sort of uh confidence on account of
containment of that of that chitta and
you don't need to like oh let me now uh
calm watch my nostrils feel the
sensations do this so that there's no
need for it because the animal is
already relatively calm from how it used
to be because you haven't been acting
out towards provoking sights sounds
smell taste touches and thoughts and the
result of that is well the animal is not
as provoked.
So that's that's kind of pretty much the
the core of the training boils down to
that and remains the same throughout. As
I said all these other stages that the
Buddha introduces here it's obviously
you know they were visible to him and
could have been visible to Kundalia but
often more than not they were completely
not even mentioned and he was just
purification of the action by body
speech and mind which obviously includes
your intentions now um not allowing the
center stage not entertaining for
anything unh wholesome not acting out of
doubt and those were those are the
practical ways of of studying your
chitta When that cheetah is steady, when the
When that cheetah is steady, when the
cheetah is withdrawn from the u and
wholesome from the when he when he has
overcome lost the concern and displeasure in
lost the concern and displeasure in
regard to the entire world,
then what you're left with is the
clarity of mindfulness. And then you
could see body within the body, feeling
within the feeling, mind within the
mind, phenomena within phenomena.
So chitta is steady by preventing it to
move. It cannot move accidentally or
like oh I I I lost I I um I forgot about
things for a split second. My cheetah
moved. No, your idea of cheetah moved.
You forget things for a split second or
longer. Cheetah still didn't move. Why?
Because you didn't act out of those
things. It moves when you open the
gates. and you open the gates when you
act towards sight, sounds, smell, taste,
touches and entertain unh wholesome
thoughts. So that's why pretty much that sila that
So that's why pretty much that sila that
training that sensory train that virtue
is your samadei is what samadei is and
it just continues growing from there.
Um
so so yeah maybe to also address just
like a question like so phenomenon when
you say he contemplates mental
phenomenon. So what what's a phenomenon
in the most say in the most practical
terms um well phenomenon is literally anything
um well phenomenon is literally anything
that appears. Doesn't matter where it
appears. Doesn't matter whether it
appears as a sight, sound, smell, taste,
touch or as an idea or as a memory or as
a non-defined idea or as an ambiguous
feeling or doesn't matter in and of
itself. Anything that can be designated
is real as such
and that is a phenomenon. So you
recognize that phenomenological nature
of things as in they don't ex like say
oh is it that do do these things exist
in the world or in my head? You realize
well the thought of the world is already
a phenomena. The thought of my head it's
already a phenomena. So whether I place
it in my head or the world it will be
secondary to the actually arisen
phenomenon of the world the thought of
the world image of the world and the
image of my head. So that's how you
would transcend both internal and
external in that sense by recognizing
the phenomena are. That's pretty much
all you can say about them. But anything
anything you can think of, anything you
can perceive to that extent it's real as
such. And even if it's you can't quite
put your finger on it, it always sort of
slips through. You can't quite define
it. It's real as such as a nondefinable
always slipping through thing that
you're trying to think.
So that's what phenomena in terms of the
seven factors of enlightenment. We could
just mention perhaps that um
so fulfilling the factor of
recollection, the factor of sati, the
factor of uh not falling away from the
right perspective, from the right
context. No, no matter what comes to
your senses through animal not being
provoked towards sight, sounds, smell,
taste, touches,
you are already um staying within the
same context through not acting out
towards things that are unbeneficial by
body, speech and mind. You are
maintaining the right context. So that's
why I said like once you start
recognizing this, you realize, oh, this
is quite good because it's effortless. I
don't need to do anything on top of it
to to develop the factor of to keep it
together. I must concentrate. I must
concentrate. Oh, accidentally I lost it.
I lost it. It slipped my mind. You just
need to not intentionally choose to go
against the principles that you would
have been developed.
Um so there's loads of room for for for
for uh for breeding so to speak.
So same investigation of phenomena
investigation of the nature of things as
you have to say especially when you pick
the specific
uh universally kind of relevant
phenomena such as
tanha craving ownership um like all
these subtle background things that that
kind of you know manifest but cannot be
quite uh coarsely defined all those
things become discern your own mind
chitta signs of your mind it's a form of
seeing basically chitta the animal as an
actual living phenomenon
that lives neither here nor there so to
speak not in the world of the senses nor
in your point of view but it's it's kind
of there in between real as such that's
the point people can think about the
chitta but for them they either place it
either oh it's in my head or it's in the
world as I said they already pervert the
order by thinking it second to what it
actually is so you need to and and there
is no amount of thinking that you can do
they will re reveal it for you unless
that thinking it's paired based upon
comes out of virtue and sense restraint.
So that's as I said many times before
that's what creates allows that new
dimension new perspective new point of
view to kind of be built upon
internally. So then obviously uh once the clarity uh
So then obviously uh once the clarity uh
is the is is is developed through the
investigation phenomena rightly energy
arises energy brings the joy and
pleasure that results in calm padi and
that results in samadei composure
which then obviously all kind of
culminates in the factor of immovability
complete equinimity and dispassion.
So you could see again how completely
upside down the the modern views are of
well I'll just pick this composure the
sixth factor that's result that's kind
of predicated on five factors before and
three right behavior four foundational
mindfulness before that and three right
behaviors before that and full-on sense
restraint perfection before that. No,
I'll just pick the samadi and any
physical kind of sensations that I would
have sort of um become familiar and have
affinity towards I'll I'll do that to
calm me to pacify me and then everything
else we kind of reemerge somehow in in
in um retroactively.
Yeah. Well, good luck with that. though.
Um, so I think that um that concludes
the the sut.